<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blogdown on Deciphering Life: One Bit at a Time</title>
    <link>/tags/blogdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blogdown on Deciphering Life: One Bit at a Time</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Robert M Flight</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/blogdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Comments enabled via utterances</title>
      <link>/post/comments-enabled-via-utterances/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/comments-enabled-via-utterances/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR Utterances is a lightweight commenting platform built on GitHub issues. So you have to have a GitHub account, but I expect most people who comment on this blog already have one.
 Why Utterances When I switched to blogdown, I lost my disqus comments. I had considered migrating them over, but never got around to it. I also thought that there had to be a way to link GitHub issues to blog posts, but didn’t investigate it much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Deployment Script</title>
      <link>/post/custom-deployment-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/custom-deployment-script/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR Use a short bash script to do deployment from your own computer directly to your *.github.io domain.
 Why? So Yihui recommends using Netlify, or even Travis-CI in the Blogdown book. I wasn’t willing to setup a custom domain yet, and some of my posts involve a lot of personally created packages, etc, that I don’t want to debug installation on Travis. So, I wanted a simple script I could call on my laptop that would copy the /public directory to the repo for my github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking to Manually Inserted Images in Blogdown / Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/linking-to-manually-inserted-images-in-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/linking-to-manually-inserted-images-in-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Manual Linking? Using blogdown for generating websites and blog-posts from Rmarkdown files with lots of inserted code and figures seems pretty awesome, but sometimes you want to include a figure manually, either because you want to generate something manually and convert it (say for going from SVG of lots of points to hi-res PNG), or because it is a figure from something else (like this figure from wikipedia).
 Where to?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>